<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5357 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5357.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4656 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4656.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6038 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6038.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5938 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5938.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc5357.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-sp-ippm-monitor-services-kpi-00">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Service KPIs using TWAMP implementation">Monitoring Service KPIs using TWAMP - Implementation</title>

    <author fullname="Srivathsa Sarangapani" surname="Sarangapani">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>560079</code>
          <country>INDIA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 9845052354</phone>
        <email>srivathsas@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Peyush Gupta" surname="Gupta">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>T-313, Keerti Royal Apartment, Outer Ring Road</street>
          <city>Bangalore</city>
          <region>Karnataka</region>
          <code>560043</code>
          <country>INDIA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 9449251927</phone>
        <email>peyushg@juniper.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Vinayak Hegde" initials="V." surname="Hegde">
      <organization>Consultant</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Brahma Sun City, Wadgaon-Sheri</street>
          <city>Pune</city>
          <region>Maharashtra</region>
          <code>411014</code>
          <country>INDIA</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+91 944984401</phone>
        <email>vinayakh@gmail.com</email>
	<uri>http://www.vinayakhegde.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2015" />

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Network Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>template</keyword>

    <abstract>
     <t>We are using a new method to calculate services KPIs and metrics in the network using TWAMP protocol. The services here ranging from subscriber aware services to security application, Traffic load balancing, content delivery, real time streaming and like.The KPIs discussed in this draft include Service Latency, Serviced Packets Count, Serviced Subscriber Count, Application Liveliness and Session load per Service. KPIs monitoring of these services therefore, play a vital role in optimum usage of network resources such as capacity and throughput. Once we have the attributes like service latency, the network topology can be chosen to provide better quality of experience to the end user. For different services, the attributes may vary and our design takes care of supporting different KPIs for different services model. Additionally, liveliness of application and servers can be monitored using this proposed solution.</t>
    </abstract>

    </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t> The TWAMP-Test runs between a Session-Sender and a Session-Reflector <xref target="RFC5357">RFC&nbsp;5357</xref>. The existing TWAMP-Test packet format has existing padding octets that are currently not used (either set to zero or pseudo-random values). These octets can be used to carry additional information between the Session-Sender and the Session-Reflector. The proposed extension uses these padding octets and provide a method to monitor services KPIs in the network. This feature is termed as Services KPI Monitoring using TWAMP.</t>

      <t> The services here refers to Layer 4 to Layer 7 services like DPI, SFW, CGNAT, TDF and so on. Additionally these services can refer to applications like DNS, HTTP, FTP and so on. The KPIs MAY include service latency, service load monitoring in terms of number of flows, number of sessions, number of subscribers, number of octets, liveliness of a service.</t>

      <t>For instance, Services KPI Monitoring using TWAMP MAY be used to measure service latency of DPI, number of CGNAT flows, number of TDF subscribers and so on. Similarly this MAY be used to monitor the liveliness of the DNS Server, HTTP Server and so on.</t> 
   
      <t>As per the proposed extension, both the TWAMP-Control and the TWAMP-Test packet formats are modified. One TWAMP-Test session SHALL be used to monitor KPIs for a specific service. But there can be multiple KPIs monitored using a single test session for a specific service. A single TWAMP-Control connection MAY establish multiple TWAMP-Test sessions that measure KPIs for multiple services in the network.</t>

      <t>This extension can be used to monitor KPIs for standalone service or a set of services.</t>
       <section title="Conventions used in this document">
          <section title="Requirements Language">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
            "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
            document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
            target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
          </section>
       </section>

       <section title="Terminology">
          <t>TWAMP: Two-Way Active Measurement Protocol</t>
          <t>KPI: Key Performance Indicator</t>
          <t>DPI: Deep Packet Inspection</t>
          <t>CGNAT: Carrier Grade Network Address Translation</t>
          <t>SFW: Stateful Firewall</t>
          <t>TDF: Traffic Detection Function</t>
          <t>DNS: Domain Name Server</t>
          <t>HTTP: Hyper Text Transfer Protocol</t>
          <t>FTP: File Transfer Protocol</t>
          <t>SKMC: Services KPI Monitoring Command</t>
          <t>PDU: Protocol Data Unit</t>
       </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Services KPIs" anchor="SKPI">
       <section title="Services Keepalive Monitoring" anchor="SKM">
          <t>The Session-Sender MAY send the Service PDU as part of the TWAMP-Test Packet Padding. When Session-Reflector receives the TWAMP-Test packet, it SHALL extract the Service PDU. Then Session-Reflector SHALL inject the Service PDU to the Service Block for service processing.</t>
          <t>Based on whether the Session-Reflector received the response, the Session-Reflector SHALL decide whether the Service is alive or not.</t>

          <t>The Session-Reflector MUST start the Packet Padding with the below 4 octets as indicated in Fig.11 [TBD]. This is followed by the Service PDU (which MAY be same as whatever was sent by Session-Sender or can be the reply/response packet of the Service Block).</t>

          <t>Setting Bit 0(X) indicates that the Session-Reflector successfully sent the Service Request to the Service Block and received the response from the Service Block. If this bit is NOT set then it indicates that the Service Block is not functional.</t>
          <figure align="left" anchor="skm" title="Services Keepalive Monitoring">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
 0                   1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|X| Reserved    |          MBZ (3 octets)                       |
+++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++++
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
       </section>

       <section title="Service Latency" anchor="SL">
          <t>The Session-Sender MAY send the Service PDU as part of the TWAMP-Test Packet Padding. When Session-Reflector receives the TWAMP-Test message, it SHALL extract the Service PDU and inject that service PDU in the Service Block.</t>
 
          <t>The Session-Reflector MUST record the time, when this service PDU is injected. This SHALL be the Service latency measurement Sender Timestamp.</t>
    
          <t>Once the Session-Reflector received the Response from the Service Block, it MUST record the time. This time SHALL be the Service latency measurement Receiver Timestamp.</t> 

          <t>If the Session-Reflector does NOT receive the Service PDU (within pre configured time which is implementation specific), then it shall indicate the Service latency measurement Receiver Timestamp as 0. The Session-Reflector MUST start the Packet Padding with the 16 octets indicated below. This SHALL be followed by the Service PDU (which MAY be same as whatever was sent by Session-Sender or can be the reply/response packet of the Service Block).</t>
          <figure align="left" anchor="sl" title="Services Keepalive Monitoring">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   |      Service latency measurement Sender Timestamp             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                                                               |
   |      Service latency measurement Receiver Timestamp           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
       </section>

       <section title="Serviced Packets Count" anchor="SPC">
          <t>When Session-Reflector receives the TWAMP-Test message, it SHALL get the information about Number of Ingress Service Data packets and Number of Egress Service Data packets from the Service Block. How Session-Reflector gets this information is implemenatation dependant. Once the Session-Reflector gets this information, it MUST start the Packet Padding with the below 16 octets. This SHALL be followed by the actual Packet Padding.</t>
          <figure align="left" anchor="spc" title="Serviced Packets Count">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Number of Ingress Service Data packets                |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Number of Egress Service Data packets                 |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
       </section>

       <section title="Serviced Bytes Count" anchor="SBC">
          <t>When Session-Reflector receives the TWAMP-Test message, it SHALL get the information about Number of Ingress Service Data bytes and Number of Egress Service Data bytes from the Service Block. How Session-Reflector gets this information is implemenatation dependant. Once the Session-Reflector gets this information, it MUST start the Packet Padding with the below 16 octets. This SHALL be followed by the actual Packet Padding.</t>
          <figure align="left" anchor="sbc" title="Serviced Bytes Count">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Number of Ingress Service Data bytes                  |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |         Number of Egress Service Data bytes                   |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
             ]]></artwork>
         </figure>
       </section>

       <section title="Serviced Subscriber Count" anchor="SSC">
          <t>When Session-Reflector receives the TWAMP-Test message, it SHALL get the below information :</t>
          <t>Total Number of Subscribers      : Total number of subscribers that are currently present for the Service + 1. This count includes Active, Non-Active and any other type of subscribers.</t>

          <t>Number of Active Subscribers     : Number of subscribers who are currently Actively using the Service + 1. The meaning of Active MAY vary from Service to Service and this is implementation specific.</t>

          <t>Number of Non-Active Subscribers : Number of subscribers who are currently NOT Actively using the Service + 1. The meaning of NOT Active MAY vary from Service to Service and this is implementation specific.</t>

          <t>Number of Subscribers Added      : Number of subscribers who were NEWLY added compared to the last time the statistics was taken + 1.</t>

          <t>Number of Subscribers Deleted    :Number of subscribers who were deleted, preempted compared to the last time the statistics was taken + 1.</t>

          <t>Any of the above field can be 0 if that statistics is not supported or not valid for a particular service. Session-Reflector should always fill the value by increasing the actual service statistics by 1. Say for example, if Numer of Active Subscribers is 0, then Session-Reflector would fill this field as 1. When Session-Sender receives this value, it should subtract 1 from the received value and use it.</t> 
          <t>How Session-Reflector gets this information is implemenatation dependant. Once the Session-Reflector gets this information, it MUST start the Packet Padding with the below 40 octets. This SHALL be followed by the actual Packet Padding.</t>
          <figure align="left" anchor="ssc" title="Serviced Subscriber Count">
              <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
0                   1                   2                   3
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               Total Number of Subscribers                     |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               Number of Active Subscribers                    |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               Number of Non-Active Subscribers                |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               Number of Subscribers Added                     |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|               Number of Subscribers Deleted                   |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
              ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
       </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>We would like to thank Perceival A Monteiro for their comments, suggestions, reviews, helpful discussion, and proof-reading</t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>TWAMP Services KPIs Registry</t>
      <t>IANA is requested to reserve and maintain the below Services KPIs:</t> 

      <texttable anchor="SKreg" title="TWAMP Services KPIs Registry">
        <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Explanation</ttcol>

        <c>0</c>
        <c>None</c>
        <c></c>
        <c>1</c>
        <c>Keepalive</c>
        <c>Whether the respective service is running or not</c>
        <c>2</c>
        <c>Service Latency</c>
        <c>Service Latency which SHALL include the transit time and actual service time</c>
        <c>4</c>
        <c>Serviced Packets Count</c>
        <c>Number of ingress and egress packets for the respective service</c>
        <c>8</c>
        <c>Serviced Bytes Count</c>
        <c>Number of ingress and egress bytes for the respective service.</c>
        <c>16</c>
        <c>Serviced Subscriber Count</c>
        <c>Number of subscribers currently active for the respective service.</c>
      </texttable>

      <t>Request-TW-Session message defined in <xref target="RFC6038"></xref>.IANA is requested to reserve 2 octets for Service ID as follows:</t>
      <texttable anchor="NSKMCap" title="New Services KPIs Monitoring Capability">
        <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Description</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Semantics</ttcol>
        <ttcol align="left">Reference</ttcol>

        <c>X </c>
        <c>Service ID</c>
        <c>2 Octets starting from offset 92th Octet</c>
        <c>This document</c>
      </texttable>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>NA</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC5357;
      &RFC6038;

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
